What you just heard,
刚才各位听到的
is Beethoven's No.3 Piano concerto.
贝多芬的第三号钢琴协奏曲
Played by the young pianist
担任钢琴演奏的
Miss Tan Wei-Ching.
是我国旅欧的年轻钢琴家谭蔚菁小姐
As you know,
各位也知道
Miss Tan is having her concert at the concert hall
谭小姐明天晚上将在艺术表演厅
tomorrow night.
举行一场演奏会
She just returned today.
谭小姐今天才回到了祖国
She is very busy,
在她百忙之中
But luckily,
我们很荣幸地
We invited her to our program,
请到了她到我们的节目里来
To talk to the classical music fans
跟我们热爱古典音乐的朋友们
in the air.
在空中见面
Hello,
喂
Hello, Miss Tan. - Please put me to extention number 2681.
- 谭小姐 您好 - 请接2681
Hello, everyone.
您好 各位听众朋友好
Hello,
喂 艺文版
can I speak to Jian Lan Shin from the cultural vision?
请找江兰心小姐
Hey Lan Shin, I am Jia-Li
喂 兰心啊 我是佳莉
Do you know the pianist who just returned,
跟你打听一个人的消息 好不好
Tan Wei-Ching?
一个刚回国的钢琴家 谭蔚菁
After the concert tomorrow,
明天演奏会以后
I will go to the Japan.
后天一大早我要去日本了
How long have your travel abroad?
您出国一共有多少年了
13 Years.
一共十三年了
Wow! 13 years. - Right.
- 哇 十三年啦 - 对
Is this your first time back to Taiwan?
这次是第一次回国 是吧
Yes
是第一次回来
How come it take so long? Are you busy at work?
这么久才回国 是因为工作上的忙碌吗
At first I stayed in school
我一开始一直在学校里头
practice a lot.
不断地练习
I also participated several competitions in Europe.
后来开始参加一些欧洲的比赛
There are many competions in a year.
那每年总有好几个了
One after another.
一个过去了又要接着准备下一个
I need to gain more experience.
所以要一直不断地吸收经验
Then I started to played in concert, one after another.
后来开始演出 也是一个接着一个的
Can you tune for me? The touch is loose.
这边的弦太松 可不可以调
Of course. But, it'll take time.
可以 不过要花很长的时间
Can you start now and finish tonight?
你现在开始调的话 晚上应该可以调好
Certainly.
我想可以 没有问题
The hotel room is settled.
酒店房间已经解决了
They found the luggage. It's in your room now.
行李也找到了 已经在你房间了
This is for you, from the hotel.
这是从酒店拿来的 给你的
What's wrong?
怎么了
It's nothing.
没关系 小意思
My sister is bringing me clean clothes.
我妹怎么还没来
How come she's not here yet?
我叫她帮我送干净的衣服过来的
She's in Taipei?
她到台北来了吗
Just moved up.
是啊
That's right. High school starts a week earlier than we do.
对了 高中比我们开学是早一点
Look at that dummy!
你看这个小笨蛋
Jia-Li, over here...
佳莉 过来过来
This is Ching-Ching. Tan Wei-Ching
这是青青 谭蔚菁
Hello.
你好
Cat got your tongue? Introduce yourself!
快 自我介绍 大方一点
Jia... I'm Lin Jia-Li.
我 叫林佳莉
Are you OK?
你没事吧
Just a little tired. I think I'll go back to my hotel.
也许太累了 我想回旅馆休息
The press conference is at three.
今天下午三点和文化界记者 有个座谈会
The limousine will be at the hotel at five-thirty,
五点半车子会到酒店 接我们去吃饭
then to dinner and the concert hall by seven.
七点到会场
There's a cocktail party in your honor after the performance.
演奏会以后 有个主办单位的酒会
We must leave no later than nine in the morning...
然后 明天早上九点 一定要从酒店出发去机场
Our Cathay Pacific Flight 450 leaves for Tokyo at 10:50 a.m.
十点五十分飞往东京
And we arrive three hours later...
飞行时间三小时半
Don't forget the press at three.
记住 茶会是三点
Birgit come over.
Birgit请过来一下
Hi
欧巴桑
You're back.
回来了
Father.
父亲
How is the weather in Taipei?
台北热吗
It seems so much hotter than usual this year.
今年的天气好像比以前热
This is the photo I took in competition when I was little.
这是我小时候钢琴比赛的照片
Is this you?
这是你啊
Yes.
对啊
This is Jia Sen.
这是佳森
He was the champion.
他拿冠军耶
And this?
那这个呢
I don't remember.
这个我不记得了
He looks like his mom.
佳森像妈妈哦
They said I look like dad.
人家都说我比较像爸爸
Agree.
我看也像
I didn well in pathology and analysis.
解剖学和病理学这次考的不错
But when it comes to dissection,
不过 每次上解剖学的时候
I always feel...
心里总是有点
Don't worry.
不要紧
I'll give you a little practice during the vacation.
这次暑假 我会好好训练你一下
But you must force yourself to watch during surgery.
开刀的时候一定要看
The closer you look
看习惯
the quicker you'll get used to it.
习惯了 就好了 知道吗
How do you like it?
你觉得习不习惯
What did you say?
你说什么
Do you feel at home here?
你习不习惯我们家
It's fine.
还好
Just smells a little like a hospital.
不过好像一直有股药的味道
Can we cancel this afternoon's press conference?
今天下午的茶会 可不可以取消
I'll see what I can do...
当然可以 不过
But why?
为什么
There's someone I must go and see.
有一位朋友很想见我
It's that hotel message, isn't it?
很重要的一位老朋友
I don't know if I should go or not.
我不知道我该不该去
You go if you think you should.
你认为该去 你就去
But remember,
我认为
A pianist should concentrate on the performance.
我无法忍受一位钢琴家无法集中精神的音乐会
Relax and I'll take care of the press conference.
不用担心 我会处理下午的茶会
How did you find me?
你怎么找到我的
From a journalist friend.
我向报社的朋友打听的
Hot coffee.
热咖啡
How long has it been?
多少年了
13 years.
十三年了
You left in a hurry.
那个时候 你突然间出国了
I'm not even sure when you left.
你哪天走的 我都不知道
The scholarship was a bit of a surprise.
奥国的奖学金来得突然了一点
School was starting and they expected me in Vienna right away.
而且马上就要开学了
I was in a rush.
走得很匆忙
I guess a lot of water has passed under the bridge...
也许有很多事情已经过去了
But I think you ought to know.
可是我还是希望你能够知道
I tried more than once to get in touch with you.
我曾经去找过你好多次
I wanted to tell you...
就是想跟你讲
Is Ching-Ching home, Mrs. Tan?
伯母 青青在不在
No, she's not in.
不在家
When will she be back?
她什么时候回来
I'm not sure. She's been getting in very late lately.
不知道 她最近回来都很晚
It was only later I heard you'd gone to Europe.
后来就听说你出国了
Do you remember
你还记不记得 我考上大学的那个暑假
Come on. Choose one.
快点决定 你挑一样
Call it my graduation gift.
算是我给你考上大学的礼物
Go ahead dummy!
不要不好意思嘛
My paycheck can take it.
我已经毕业实习 赚钱了
It's from Ching-ching.
这是青青送我的
What's up?
怎么 不喜欢回家啊
Can't bare to go home and leave Ching-ching?
还是离不开青青
Home to dinner with Dr. Chen.
陈妇产科他们要请我们吃饭
Still trying to set you up with his daughter?
还是那相亲的事啊
Dr. Chen and dad were at medical school together in Japan.
陈妇产科是爸爸在日本读医的老同学
They grew up together.
又是同乡
Chen's practive
他的诊所和我们家的林外科
is as well-known as Dad's.
可以说是一样的有名
School starts in July, doesn't it, Jia Sen?
佳森 七月半以前 你开学了吗
So it's settled.
那这样 我们就决定
You'll exchange rings with Wan-jen in early July,
七月半前 给你跟婉真戴戒指
and we'll set the wedding for the Autumn festival.
结婚仪式 我们就定在中秋节
Or should we wait another month until Confucius' Day?
或是孔子诞辰纪念日
Everyone has a day or two off.
那个时候 亲戚朋友都休息
They will be able to come.
大家才会来
What do you think?
你有什么意见
It's fine if you don't have other oppinions.
假使没有那最好
Then Tetso can attend his sister's wedding before he goes overseas.
这样哲夫也可以参加他姐姐的婚礼之后再出国
Tetso, if possible,
哲夫 假使快的话
you'll have you Ph. D, in four years.
四年后你就拿到博士学位了
Jia-li will graduate at that time.
那时候佳莉也已经毕业了
I'll be out of another wedding gift!
我看 我的红包是跑不掉
I hardly even know Wan-jen.
我对阿真一点都不了解
If you marry Wan-jen,
而且这样子做的话
what about Ching-Ching?
青青怎么办
It's not fair.
这太不公平了
What's your problem?
是怎么了
You know.
你也知道
Jia-sen is taking the whole thing very sensibly.
佳森是一个很懂事的孩子
Jia-sen?
阿森
He certainly knew how to let himself off the hook.
他倒是有发泄自己的办法
No, I shouldn't have said that.
我不应该这么说的
What chance do we have
年纪这么大了
when it comes to honor... face.
还是没有办法摆脱 那些面子 担子
It's all so superficial.
全是表面的东西
Sometimes my hypocrisy scares me.
有的时候我觉得自己 真的虚伪的可怕
The way we protect ourselves is phoney.
我想 人在想保护自己的时候总是虚假的吧
Like insects changing its colors.
就像那种虫有保护色的
To tell the truth, I had no desire to go abroad.
其实 我根本不想去奥国
All I ever wanted was to make a little money teaching,
只想教教琴 赚点钱
and wait for your brother graduate.
等你哥哥毕业
But we broke up.
后来这些计划完全改变了
Everything changed.
和佳森断了以后
All that was left was the music.
除了钢琴之外 我什么都没有了
And all I wanted was to leave.
那时候 我只想离开这里
I know you came looking for me,
我知道你来找过我
but what use was there in meeting?
可是我没有见你
Words couldn't change a thing.
我见了你又能改变什么呢
Is Ching-ching home, Mrs. Tan?
伯母您好 请问青青在不在
No, she isn't in.
她不在
Will she be back soon?
什么时候回来
I'm not sure. She's been getting in very late.
不知道 她最近回来都很晚
Please give this letter on to her.
麻烦您把这封信交给她好不好
Sure. - Thank you.
好一谢谢
Goodbye.
再见
This is for you.
你的信
I hadn't the courage to see you to this very day!
到刚才我都还没有勇气来见你
Married?
结婚了吧
Your parent's choice?
家里安排的
What're you having?
你吃什么
It's Ah-Tsai.
那就是阿财
Ah-Tsai! Over here!
阿财
Sit here!
坐这儿
I'm Ah-Tsai.
我是阿财
This is Chen De-Wei. What do they call you?
这是程德伟 你是
Lin Jia-li. Western Languages.
林佳莉 外文系的
Interested?
怎么样
Not specially.
没怎么样啊
All right!
好啊
Afterwards?
后来呢
This dump is mine, now.
现在这是我的地方
Everything you see is mine.
全都是我的
I can hardly hear myself think.
吵死了
My old man picked up the mortgage
我老头的一个朋友做生意倒了
when a friend of his went broke.
当初他把这个房子抵押给我老头
Now the old man's passing it on to me.
现在我老头又把它交给了我
No power?
怎么没电
No water.
水也没有
Little fucker couldn't pay. They cut if off eons ago.
小子欠多了 早剪了
When do you move in?
那你什么时候搬进来
Who knows.
我也不晓得
Possibly next week
说不定下礼拜
My old man might have to mortgage it himself!
我老头又把它抵押给别人了
Creep!
讨厌啦
De-wei is a bit of a childish.
程德伟是孩子气了一点
But he's straight, and that has its advantages.
不过老实人有老实人的好处
No matter what,
不管怎么样
At least he won't walk out,
除非你把他给甩了
unless you drop him first.
要不然他不会跑掉 对不对
Take a chance
如果不满意的话
You can always find someone else,
还可以再找啊
if you're not satisfied.
找到好的最好
And he'll always be around,
找不到更好的
if you don't find anything better.
他还在那里啊
De-wei'll be training all summer.
暑假德伟受训
What about you? Going home?
你呢 回家啊
Let's get together before you go
走以前通知我一下 我们聚聚
Bye!
拜
Are you all done with your finals?
你还有几科
One more to go.
还有一科
Ah-Tsai stole his Dad's money to play the market.
阿财偷他爸爸的钱去做股票
His old man caught him, now he's afraid to go home.
被抓到了 不敢回去
I'm leaving for the army tomorrow.
我明天下午的火车去左营
I know
我知道
Your family never interfered?
家里没有干涉你吗
Father was a little more tactful with me.
爸这次做得比较技巧一点
As soon as I graduated.
我毕业了以后
He rented out the Taipei house
他就把台北的房子给租出去了
I had no choice but to move back home.
这么一来 我只好搬回家去住了
It was only with De-wei gone off to the army
德伟去当兵以后
that I realized he wasn't there anymore, I was kind of dazed.
我才感觉到他不在了
At that time,
其实那个时候
I hardly know what I was doing.
我也是迷迷糊糊的
Four years of college were over just like that
不敢相信大学四年就这样过去了
Like everyone else,
我也像其他人一样
I took a toefl tested and applied to schools,
没有什么目的地去考留考
I don't know what I really want.
申请学校 去考托福
De-wei wrote me often during his service;
德伟自从去当兵了以后常常写信给我
He's no poet,
他不是一个很会写信表达自己的人
but his letters gave me
但是每一次收到他的信
a sense of contentment.
都会感到一种很满足的幸福
But two years is a long time to wait,
好不容易捱到德伟退伍了
and he often asked me
好几次 他来信都要我到台北去
to meet him in Taipei.
和他见面
Come, Jia-li.
佳莉 你出来一下
An American Ph.d. In just four and half years.
哲夫才四年半就拿到美国电机博士
Tetso's no fool.
也真不简单
Your father always hoped you would marry such a man.
你爸爸也希望你能嫁给一个很实在的人
You should keep that in mind,
有时候 你也该替他想想看
and think a little of your future.
最好 你也要为自己打算一下
It's hard to imagine a more satisfying day in my whole life!
这辈子 恐怕没有比今天更轻松的了
Dr. Chen and I have agreed
我和陈先生商量的结果
on an August engagement.
八月中就要让佳莉和哲夫订婚
Jia-li can then go abroad with Tetso
然后一起出国
just in time for school.
佳莉也正好赶的上开学
A son and a daughter.
一个儿子一个女儿
It's all settled.
两个人都替他们安排好了
So that's a great weight off my mind.
心事也了一半
My ideas have changed a lot since college.
从毕业以后一直到现在 思想上改变了很多
People say I have matured.
很多人都说我成熟了
I think it's more a question of the way
也许是以前比较容易把事情想的
we'd idealize things
比较理想一点
and the extent of our ambition.
野心自然也就比较大
And now?
现在呢
I try not to expect too much of the future.
不太去想将来
I don't ask much,
也不 不会去期望些什么
Just hope for
只希望说 在日常生活当中
a share of the small pleasures of life.
能够得到一些小的满足
Like a good piece of music
就像是收到当年球队朋友写来的信啊
or a letter from old team-mates back in college.
或者是听了一首好听的音乐
But I have no right to be telling you what to do.
我也没什么资格告诉你什么
What can I possibly tell you?
我能告诉你什么吗
I just wanted to know are you happy?
我只想问你 你快乐吗
First tell me what you call "happiness?"
你先告诉我 什么叫做快乐
With all that education
你也是大学毕业
you should know what happiness is.
你应该知道快乐是什么
De-wei it's for you!
程德伟 外找
Have a sit.
坐
I'll arrange a couple of tickets for my concert.
晚上带德伟来听我的音乐会
Bring De-wei along.
我给你们弄两张贵宾票
Not tonight.
今天晚上 我不能去
I... let me put it this way
我 这样讲好了
Something happened three years ago.
三年以前 发生了这么一件事
I remember it so clearly-like that morning.
我还记得那是一个充满了希望的清晨
The air so fresh and full of promise.
我是在清新的空气里
For the first time in my life I knew
真的 是第一次能够了解那种
a kind of contentment.
清淡的幸福
I could almost smell the greenness of the leaves.
第一次能够了解青色叶子的清香
I walked all the way home.
我一直走路回家
I hadn't felt so good in ages.
很久没有这么享受过了
But the moment I walked in the apartment door.
可是 我一到家
The maid told me
我们的女佣就告诉我
the police had found De-wei on some beach;
警察打过电话来说德伟在一个海边
Drowned.
淹死了
The duty officer will be a while.
我们巡佐去连络海防部队了
He's getting some coastguard frogmen
找人来捞 你先生的尸体
to drag for your husband's body.
可能要等一下才能回来
How did it happen?
是怎么样发生的
It's none of my business, really.
这个我 我也不知道怎么说
But as far as I can tell...
大概是这样
I'd collected my nets
昨天太阳下山时 我收好网子要回家
There was this city guy;
看见一位都市人
tall and skinny... sitting over there;
高高瘦瘦的 坐在那边
I could see it clear as day, he was frowning.
眉头很皱 我看的很清楚
I saw him too, it was darker now.
我也有看到 那个时候天也黑了
I thought it was strange
我心里在想 奇怪
to go swimming at that time of day.
这么晚了还要游泳
I truned and looked
我一直回头看着
Later, after dinner,
后来 差不多八点多
must've been around eight,
吃饱了晚饭
When the tide was high...
海水正在涨潮
We were down on the beach around dawn this morning.
今天天亮的时候我们就去海边
And found these things of your husband's
捡到一些你先生的东西
A bottle with your husband's name.
我捡到的药罐子上面有你先生的名字
It was... Cheng... De-wei, right?
叫程德伟 对不对
The Duty Officer looked forever in the phonebook,
巡佐要找那家诊所的电话找了好久
before he found that... something Luo's Health Clinic,
那家诊所叫 什么卫生诊所 对不对
But I don't remember my husband going to any Dr. Luo
不过我不记得我先生有没有去过这家诊所
Do you think it might be some other Chen De-wei?
会不会是同名同姓
I'm not too clear.
这个我也不知道
You should ask the officer
这个要问巡佐 我也不知道
Wait here.
你在这里等一下
He's coming.
他马上就回来
Take care of this, will you?
这个处理一下
Ok.
好
I've seen your translation, Miss Li
林佳莉 你翻的东西我看了一下
It's not quite what I expected
好像味道不太对
from a language major like yourself.
你不是外文系毕业的吗
I don't want to tell you how to do your job
我想 我不必告诉你怎么翻吧
You are in charge of the translation
你看 那边的东西 后面的东西
for all these documents in future.
将来都是由你来翻
Your incompetence is rather unsettling!
你这点东西搞不定 我怎么办
Come on, De-wei
德伟
You see
你看
Come.
走
Hey!
喂
What?
什么事啊
De-wei!
德伟
Where are you?
你现在在那里
What the hell's happened?
到底发生什么事
Take your time.
你慢慢讲
Ah-tsai announced his marriage around this time
那个时候 阿财突然宣布结婚了
The eternal playboy, Ah-Tsai
那个一向风流成性
with four or five girls forever in tow, marrying!
同时能够周旋在四五个女朋友之间的阿财
T only made sense later, when we found out
其实 后来我才知道理由很简单
that he'd married the daughter of some big financier.
阿财娶的是永利财团老板的大女儿
It came as no surprise when not much later
果然不出所料隔了没多久
Ah-tsai was named his father-in-law's new Corporate Chairman.
他就成为他岳父财团的一家关系企业的董事长
Right away he strengthened his position
为了要扩大他自己的力量
by gathering a loyal group of old buddies
阿财就招集了一群以前的好朋友
to work with him.
跟他一起打天下
De-wei and Ah-tsai had grown up together
德伟从小就跟阿财一起长大 一道上学
they were closest in school or on the basketball court
球场上 他们一直也是最有默契的搭配
they were even stationed in the same army service unit
连当兵 都分到同一个单位
So it was only natural
所以 很自然的
that De-wei became Ah-tsai's general manager
德伟就成了他的总经理
Morning call, Mr. Manager. Wake up, sir.
总经理 起床啦
Aren't you the one who's always saying
你不是说激励员工最好的办法
Late managers get late workers?
就是第一个进办公室吗
Just another five minutes.
再五分钟就好了
My head's killing me.
昨天实在太晚睡了
Look who's complaining.
谁要你去应酬到那么晚
It's not all dinner and dancing, you know
也不光是应酬
You can't imagine,
你想像不到
there are so many things to do.
事情实在太多了
Everyday's the same
每天都是这个样子
I arrive office, take off my coat,
刚进办公室 没喘几口气
and the day's already done.
一天就过去了
So I come home with this strange anxiety
每天回到家想睡觉时总觉得不甘心
that I've left so much undone
好像很多事情没做一样
Do you like hanging around here or going to work better?
你觉得上班好 还是闲在家里好
I don't have my feet up all day either, you know
我在家里也没闲着
Even with a maid,
虽然现在有请佣人
there's a lot I take care of myself.
可是 还是有很多事都是我在做
Shopping, cleaning, pressing your clothes
整理房间 买菜 给你烫衣服
While you're working for others, I'm here working for us
我是觉得 上班好像替别人在做事
I've been thinking of
我喜欢替自己做
taking a class in flower arranging
我最近还想去学插花
But it's still not fair
实在太不公平了
I have to get up every morning,
我每天要这么早起床
while you sleep in
你还可以赖床
Next time you entertain,
以后你要去应酬的话
at least give me a call.
记得打电话给我
Pay attention, now
是 是这样子
Fix the stem about one-third of the way in,
差不多在三分之一的地方固定起来
with the chrysanthemums at an angle of forty-five degrees
接着在菊花全长 约三分之二的地方
Take care with the petals to the front and back
在水中剪掉角度45度的位置
Hsin-hsin
欣欣
Jia-li
佳莉
How old is your child?
你小孩多大了
Come on over.
到我那儿坐坐吧
I live nearby
我就住在这附近
Not today. De-wei will be off any minute now
今天不行 德伟就要下班了
So you did marry De-wei!
你真的跟德伟结婚了
He's hardly ever home for dinner... he's working very hard
他现在很忙 难得回家吃一次饭
So I want to be there for him tonight
所以我一定要回去
Promise to come and see me
这样的话 你就回去吧
in a day or two
过两天到我那儿来坐坐
there's so much I want to tell you!
我有好多话想告诉你
It's true.
真的啦
They will hold a singing competition?
他们要招考歌星啊
The wife if back.
我们太太回来了
Let me help you
太太 回来了
I am late.
我回来晚了
We'll have to move fast
我们要快一点
De-wei'll be home any minute
先生马上就要下班了
First, take a vase for the flowers
你把花盆先拿出来
OK.
好
Then put the fruit in the fridge
把水果拿去洗一洗 放在冰箱里
Have her wait a moment
叫她等一等
OK
好
Hello
喂
This is he.
我是 是
OK
0K
The deal is confirmed.
鸿伟的案子成了
Great!
搞定搞定
We will make a fortune! Cool, a 7 milliard deal!
噱海了
Let's party tonight!
走 今天晚上我们要好好的疯一次
Let's go!
走
You're still here.
你还没走啊
I will have a look of your proposal.
你们公司的案子我明天再看一看
Let's have dinner together.
我们一块吃饭去
De-wei! Move your ass
德伟 走了
It didn't even cross your mind.
你都不记得了
Tonight is our third anniversary.
今天是我们结婚三周年
The apartment's my mother's.
这是我妈的房子
After all the crap I've been through.
混了这么多年
I don't even end up with a place of my own!
连一栋自己的房子都没有混到
Hush, too hot to sleep?
好了嘛 乖孙子 你就睡吧
Shh... Grandma will fan you
热了是不是 奶奶给你褊褊
All I got for my trouble was that fatherless kid.
只有这个没有爸爸的属于我的
Remember that visiting professor?
你还记不记得那个客座教授
I wasted two whole years with that bastard
跟他混了两年多
expecting him to take me back to the States.
本来希望他能带我到美国去
Before I found out he'd been married for years
结果人家是有老婆的
Next it was a businessman...
后来认识了一个做生意的
Ah-tsai might know the guy
搞不好阿财也认识
He ran away and left debts.
结果那小子欠人家一屁股债 跑了
He only left the baby.
只留下这个
At that time,
那个时候
I don't know why I will keep the baby.
我怎么会想到把他留下来呢
How does De-wei treat you?
德伟对你还好吧
De-wei's always been a straight-shooter
德伟还真是挺老实的
Remember back in college
在学校的时候
how I'd always be telling you this and showing you that
我教你这个 教你那个
I wish there was someone who could teach me a thing or two, now
现在谁来教我这个 教我那个
It's beautiful.
哇 那么漂亮
Thank you.
谢谢
You're really making progress!
进步的很快
Very impressive.
非常的漂亮
You have such lively color and line.
花和枝叶表现的很活
I hope you will do even more beautiful work at home
回家以后也请你插的更漂亮
Thank you, I will.
好 谢谢
It's me. I can't come home tonight.
是我 今天晚上我不回家了
I have to go first thing in the morning to look over a Taichung site.
明天一大早约好在台中工业区去看一块地
I'll drive down there tonight.
我今天下了班就下去
Don't wait for me.
不要等我了
OK
好
Please.
好嘛
Come one.
讨厌
Stop.
不要这样嘛
No.
不要
See, your wife
你看 你太太
Go home, your wife if waiting.
快回去 你太太在等你
Go home.
回去啦
De-wei
德伟
Do you hear me? I'm talking to you!
我跟你说话你听到没有
What is that supposed to mean?
你这算什么嘛
Are you trying to punish me?
惩罚我是不是
You think I want to snoop on you like this?
你以为我喜欢查你的行踪
It's been two years of business trips and entertaining
这两年来
And not once have I questioned you, or doubted what you've said
你在外面什么事情我都不会多过问
because I know you wouldn't tolerate it
因为我知道你不喜欢我多过问
But you're gone from morning until late at night
可是你每天早出晚归的
without even a phone call sometimes
有的时候连一个电话都没有
How should I know where you are? Or who you're with?
我怎么知道你在哪里 跟谁在一起
I wouldn't even know if something'd happen to you
会发生什么事情
All I can do is sit at home nursing my fears
我会在家里胡思乱想的
Maybe that's all you'll ever nurse!
你就会胡思乱想
How often have I told you to stop worrying
我告诉过你多少次了
and to stay out of my work space
我有我工作范围的空间
I don't want you to interfere my work or to worry.
我不希望你干扰 更不希望你担心
What did you want at the site?
你去工地干什么
You make a fool of me.
害的我好糗 你知不知道
I am embarrassed.
我糗呆了
I work day and night.
我白天工作 晚上工作
Where am I? How, for Christ's sake, don't you know?
我在哪里 你再说我在哪里
I am working.
我在工作
I'm working for us.
为了这个家 我要工作
What do you know anyway, except how to wait for me?
你每天在家等我吃饭以外
What can you do?
你还知道什么
Flower arranging!
插花
Do you think I enjoy all this entertaining
你以为我喜欢应酬啊
I hate drinking.
我’很喝酒 你知不知道
I throw up!
回家吐
All the next day, my head aches!
第二天上班头还痛
I always have to measure up to your standards
你老是以你的标准来衡量我 来要求我
It's taken me so long to see just how selfish you are!
我发现你这个人实在太自私了
Selfish?!
谁自私
If I come home to you every night for dinner,
是不是要我每天回来陪你吃饭
would it make you happy?
让你安心
Would I be less selfish?
我就不自私
What about you!
为了我回来陪你吃饭 让你安心
With your demands to come home to keep you company
你这样要求我
You don't call that selfish?
你自己是不是很自私
De-wei,
德伟
is there no chance to get back to where we were?
难道我们不能恢复到像以前一样吗
Don't you even have a little time to share with me
难道你不能多给我一点点时间陪陪我
to bring a little warmth back to our home? Are we family?
让这个家像一个家吗
With all that I've given you
我已经给你这么多了
I just don't know what more you want
我真的不知道你还需要什么
Yes?
喂
Still tied-up?
还在忙啊
Will you be off soon?
快下班了吧
Still angry with me?
你还在生气啊
Not really
还好
OK
好
What's going on?
怎么了
The old woman's spot-checking?
老婆查勤
Keep her in line, man!
家教太差了嘛
Catch you tonight, our old table!
晚上北投见 老地方
Don't come over... I'll pick you up
你别过来 我来接你
Where are you?
你在哪里
I know the place
知道了
Can I help you?
有事吗
I just want to let you know I moved
没事 只是告诉你刚搬家
Here's my new number
我把电话留给你
I'll be getting my own place uptown
等我们这笔生意成交了以后
As soon as this deal comes through
我就可以自己买一楝房子
I will move to TienMu
搬到天母去住
Call me
打电话给我
Have you been getting enough sleep?
这几天晚上你都睡得好不好
Where do you eat?
晚上到哪里吃饭
Been anywhere in particular?
这几天你都去了什么地方
What are you trying to prove?
你这是干什么嘛
I'm just showing a little concern.
我只不过关心你而已嘛
You wouldn't be afraid if you trusted me
信任我就不该害怕
Jia-li
佳莉
Excuse me,
太太
Should we eat, Mrs. Cheng?
太太要不要开饭了
Your husband's been and gone already
先生回来又出去了
I don't know you will come.
没想到你会赶过来
I'm glad you're here
你来了正好
You're just in time to identify these
这些东西 你正好可以帮我们指认
Then sign your name here...
然后在这上面签个名
Is there anything else?
还有没有别的
You mean they're not your husband's?
这些东西不是你丈夫的
I'm not sure, I can't be certain.
我不晓得 我没有把握
You should at least recognize this.
那这些应该是他的吧
It has his name on it.
上面有他的名字
It was with all this stuff
这些东西全部在沙滩上捡到的
we found on the beach.
和其它完全一样
It could not be wrong
没有错
I spoke with this clinic on the label.
我曾经过打电话给这家诊所
About your husband's condition
了解一下你丈夫的情况
That's how I got your number.
要不然我怎么会知道你家里的电话
His doctor gave it to me.
都是诊所大夫告诉我的
But I really don't recall
可是我真的不记得
my husband seeing a psychiatrist.
我先生有去看过这个医生
I suppose he was keeping something from you.
那大概是他有所隐瞒没跟你讲
Logically speaking,
不过按照逻辑推论
There's no other explanation for his death.
这完全没有他杀的可能性
Since he was already receiving this kind of treatment
他既然去看这种医生
Do you think he might have considered suicide?
是不是有自杀的倾向
Only you could really know.
你应该比谁都清楚
Was there anything strange
那你昨天看到他的时候
About his behaviour yesterday?
他是不是有什么不对劲的地方
I don't know.
我不知道
I haven't seen him for days
我已经好几天没有看到他了
She still doesn't know!
又是不知道
Maybe he didn't kill himself
也不一定是自杀
Maybe the medicine made him drowsy, he laid down
说不定他吃了这种药之后昏睡过去
and got carried off with the tide.
被海水冲走
It's possible, don't you think?
你说是不是
Or maybe he swam way out
也说不定他游泳游得太累
and couldn't make it back.
游不回来 这也说不定哦
Honestly,
其实
I know something was wrong
我也知道有些的状况
It's all different.
和以前不太一样了
I don't know
可是我就是找不出
how to find way out...
一个好的办法去
I felt
我只是觉得
Jia-li and I are drifting further and further apart.
我跟佳莉的想法距离愈来愈远了
You know better than anyone what I...
你是知道的
In these few years
这几年来
What I been through,
我所经历的
what we been throguh
我们所经历的
is different from anything she knows
她所经历的太不一样了
The only advice I can give you
站在这么多年哥儿们的立场上
Speaking for myself and the boys...
我只想提醒你一点
Don't let the external issues
就是不要让这种工作范围以外的事
influence your moods
影响到你的情绪
and work
影响到你的工作
You and I are basically different
因为你和我不一样
I've lived this way all my life
我从小就习惯这种生活
So I can handle this kind of thing
碰到了这种事情
With one eye closed and one hand tied behind my back.
闭着眼睛我都能够应付自如
It's tough out there
左手让你
You should know
你应该知道的
This is a competetive world.
在这现实生活中的生存竞争力
The more time you waste on your minds
你如果多花一分钟在你自己的心思上面
The more people will surpass you.
别人就会超越你一分钟
I'll be straight with you
我老实的跟你讲
Don't think I will protect you if you allow personal affairs
如果因为你表现得不理想
to affect company interests
而影响到公司的利益
just because you're one of my right-hand men
我不但不能保护你
It's for that reason
就因为你是我哥儿们
that I'll make an example of you.
我更需要向他们交待
What kind of future did you have in mind?
什么是将来的幸福
Do you call these days "happy"?
这种日子你也叫幸福吗
Thanks for the encouragement.
你这个样子给我很大的阻力
Why do you always...
你为什么老是
Trust me a little, won't you?
你为什么不可以相信我呢
Let me make a go of it. Just let me try!
让我去冲 让我去闯吧
De-wei, everything you say
德伟 你这种话听起来给我一种感觉
is just one more excuse
就是藉口
Cut if off, Jia-li
又来了 佳莉
I know you're dissatisfied at the moment
我知道你现在很不快乐
Can't you think of tomorrow for a change?
可是你能不能看远一点
I promise things will be better
我将来会让你比较开心
Just be patient
你现在可不可以忍耐一下呢
I don't know anymore.
我不知道
You sound like you're preaching
这些话听起来像传教的
Trust in the lord,
如果你相信上帝
And all your wrongs will be right...
死了以后就可以进天堂
What the hell am I talking about? What are you talking about?
我在讲什么 你在讲什么
De-wei,
德伟
Maybe it's all just too trivial to worry about
或许我担心的比较肤浅一点
For God's sake, relax.
不要担心嘛
But all I've ever prayed for is today
可是我祈求的只是今天 现在
Let's stop all this fighting now, please
我们不要再像这样子吵了 好不好
I only want to lean on you. Just rest for awhile.
我只想靠着你好好地休息一下
I'm tired.
我真是好累
You'll feel a lot better
离开家一阵子吧
If you get away for awhile
会好点的
Trust me.
真的
In the future,
我们公司以后
I'm going to put you
日本 韩国 香港 新加坡的业务
in charge of all our Asian business.
我就全交给你负责
I think it'll do you good.
我想对你会有好处的
What do you think?
你觉得怎么样
Okay
0K
Hi! No trouble finding the place?
怎么样 还好找吧
Are you in a hurry?
待会儿有事
No. De-wei's abroad
没事 德伟出国了
I'll just finish up here
等一下我帮他们把这些照片拍完
and we can get out for a breath of air
我们出去逛逛
When did you move in?
你什么时候搬过来的
A week or two ago.
两个礼拜了
He's seven years younger than me
他比我小七岁
I'd only known him a couple of weeks
我们才认识两个礼拜
when he asked me to move in
他就叫我搬过来
Who could have guessed
没想到吧
at my age?
我这样的年纪
Things like this just happened.
还有那么爆炸性的事情发生
What about the chile?
小孩呢
With my mother.
在我妈那儿
You can relax in the other room.
你先到隔壁房间坐坐
I'll be with you in a minute.
我马上就来
Here
来
Ping-ping
平平
This is Jia-li
这是佳莉
and he is Ping-ping, my "old man's" best friend
这是平平 小江最好的朋友
Get to know each other
你们聊聊
Hello?
喂
Alright
好
What do you call that?
怎么搞的
Just an impulse
一时兴起 心血来潮
I like your own look.
我比较喜欢你原来的样子
I guess it was curiosity
也许是好奇心
Ping ping is different... from others
平平是一个和别人 很不一样的人
I have no idea
他真的是干什么的
What he really did
我也不清楚
He said he'd come home to write
他说他现在回国来写一本书
he'd travelled a lot- been everywhere
他一直在国外跑来跑去的
I suppose that's why...
也就是因为他去过了很多地方
he talked often of his travels
所以常听他讲他旅行的经历
to Europe, South America, the Middle East, India, Nepal...
欧洲 南美 中东 印度 尼泊尔
It's true I get around
另lJ看我到处乱跑
but I haven't a penny to my name
其实我是满穷的
There's no way I could ever settle down like you
我没办法跟你一样 结婚定下来
But maybe marriage isn't just a question of money...
其实结婚跟穷不穷没什么关系
I guess I've always been this way
不过我这个人就是这个样子
That's what I like about writing...
最适合的是写写东西
With one book I can make enough... if I sell... to go back on the road
一次能赚满多的钱
Then I travel and collect more ideas for my next book
然后到处跑跑开始写下一本
It's with me all the time
我已经养成随身带来的习惯了
Like my watch
就像你戴手表一样
In this way
这样的话
I can keep a record
我可以把我的
Of whatever comes in to my head
随时来的一些想法记录下来
Like some safe-deposit box
就像把自己的生命
for all those precious moments of life.
一段一段的保存起来一样
What do you say?
你觉得呢
I guess I've never really
我的生活很简单
thought of things that way
好像从来没想到过这些问题
Perhaps not
也许是的
but do you think you'll always want things to be so simple?
还是你一直想保持现在这么简单的生活呢
Why don't you come back with me tonight?
今天晚上去我那里 好不好
Wait here. I'll get the car.
在这里等我一下 我去开车
Dad
爸爸
Are you feeling well?
你那里不舒服
I'm not sure. That's why I came for this checkup.
就是不知道 才来台北检查
And?
现在呢
The lab report is not in yet.
报告还没下来
How's things at home?
最近家里怎么样
T's difficult to keep the practice going
愈来愈难做 人很难请
Younger doctors aren't interested in private clinics;
年轻的医生 都不待在私人诊所
They're not big enough, and the equipment's too old
他们都嫌设备太旧 规模又小
Then there's long hours
而且时间比较长 比较辛苦
We can't hold a candle to a big hospital
每样都比不上新盖的大医院
Thank god Jia-sen is about ready to take over.
还好佳森已经能够担当一面了
But it's going to be tough on him
不过很辛苦
Excuse me, Mrs. Cheng?
对不起 是程太太吗
Could I have a word or two with you?
我是德伟的一个同事
I'm a colleague of De-wei's
我可以进来坐一下吗
Come in
请进
Thank you
谢谢
My name is Liu. They call me Hsiao-hui
我姓刘 他们都叫我小惠
What I am going to say
我今天来
might startle you a little
可能会带给你一些让你吃惊的消息
But I hope you can appreciate
但是我希望你先能够了解
That I bear you no malice
我今天来跟你交换意见
I'm merely here to straighten the record.
是绝对没有任何敌意的
Now
好
I have something here that is rightfully yours...
我这里有一封应该是属于你的信
This is De-wei's writing.
这是德伟的字
It's addressed to you
是他写给你的信
But the letter inside is for you
可是里面的信是写给你的
I believe you should've received his letter to me!
我想你也应该收到了一封他写给我的信
That's hardly necessary
不用拆了
You can rest assured that the letter inside is mine.
里面的信一定是写给我的
He mixed the envelopes
他把信封放错了
With all the married men I've been with in the past
我以前也跟过很多结过婚的男人在一起
Tok great pains not to intrude on their family lives
可是我从来不介入他们的婚姻生活
But in this case,
这一次
Because of this,
因为这个
I cannot walk away,
我没有办法不被牵连进来
I felt obliged to speak with you frankly,
所以我必须当面跟你谈清楚一些事情
I sympathize your situations.
其实我也很同情你的处境
After all, I'm a woman too
我们同样都是女人的立场
In fact, I believe I can even help you
我只是想帮助你
For your own benefit
我认为你必须要早一点
I'd advise you to get better prepared
为自己做一些决定做一些安排
You must realize,
我想你也很了解
That De-wei is not exactly full of confidence
德伟不是一个很有自信的人
There's so much he's unsure of
他对很多事情都没有把握患得患失
And he has a habit of avoiding issues
而且又有逃避问题的习惯
This mistake with the letters is a perfect example.
就拿他这一次寄错信的事情来讲
He intentionally mixes the letters
我敢说他是故意的
Only he will do things like this.
也只有他会做得出来
On the one hand,
他想一方面告诉你
He wants to tell you his difficulties
他有了一个这么大的问题
On the other hand, he wants me to forgive
另一方面也告诉我
his inability to explain things to you.
他不晓得怎么跟你交待
By the time he returns
然后等他回来的时候
our reactions to the situation allow him a fairly simple choice.
再依照我们对这件事情的反应
From the beginning,
做一个比较容易的决定
I suppose I can see
也许当初我就看得出来
De-Wei is the most inexperience man in the company
德伟是他们集团里面最没有经验的一个
Winning him over was my only hope
我也知道 只要我能打通他这一个人
Of access to that tight group of theirs
我就可以打到他们圈子里头去
Perhaps others will say I used him
也许会有人说我利用德伟
During this period of time, however,
可是在这段日子里头
I've stood by him
我帮了他不少的忙
And helped him through many difficulties
也帮他解决了不少问题
Perhaps that's just one more reason
也许就是因为这样
He can't seem to do without me
他反而觉得更不能少了我
I must leave
我该走了
The only other thing I wanted to tell you
我想 我最后要强调的也就是
Is not to lose anymore sleep over De-wei and me
你以后可以完全不必担心
We're through
我跟德伟之间还会发生什么事
This whole thing
因为这件事情
has brought me too much trouble.
已经带给我太多的麻烦
And I hate trouble
我是一个很怕麻烦的人
Just one question. Do you love him?
告诉我 你爱他吗
I imagine that you grew up
我想你生长的环境
In a very peaceful, story-book world
一定很安适 很浪漫
The world I grew up in taught me
我生长的环境就告诉我
That it's a world without love
这世界上没有爱
Perhaps you will find a moment or two of passion...
也许会有短暂的冲动
But there's not much
只不过如此而已
So we've read all these books
我们读过那么多书
And taken test after test
小时候一关一关的考试
But nobody's taught us
为什么没有人教过我们
How to handle the big questions like this
怎么样去面对这么重要的难题
In every book, and every movie
不管是小说还是电影
It's always the same
总是两个人结婚以后 都是圆满大结局
They all marry and live happily ever after
大结局以后呢
But after that?
大结局
Nobody told us.
没有人教过我们
And there's no practice run or on-the-job training
也没有给我们任何练习的机会
I haven't slept in days.
我己经好几天没有睡觉了
I can't
根本也睡不着
I lie down and my mind is full of questions
我一躺下来 满脑子都是问题
De-wei will be back in a few days
再过几天德伟就会回来了
But I don't know how to face him
我不知道该怎么去面对他
These might help
这个应该对你有帮助
Get a good night's rest.
好好睡一觉
At least it'll help you forget
起码可以忘掉一些烦恼
Do you think you'll divorce De-wei?
你会不会跟德伟离婚
It'd be such a waste to give up just like that
就这样放弃了 好像太可惜了
Where's Jia-li?
佳莉哪里去
Where does she go?
她跑去哪里了呢
Where am I?
这是什么地方
I must leave.
我要回去
De-wei is getting off work.
德伟要下班了
Take it easy,
你不要急
Mrs. Cheng Relax, you're still weak
程太太 你现在人还很虚弱
Just now,
所以一定要好好休息
When the doctor was in to see you
刚才医生还来看过你
He left specific instructions for you to get more rest
特别交待 你一定要多休息哦
Hsin-hsin have you been here long? - Take a good rest.
- 欣欣 - 好好休息吧
Will you keep me company?
你一直陪着我吗 欣欣
I will.
我会的
You're the only one left
我只剩下你这么一个朋友了
It's like we're back in school again
好像又回到学校一样
I'm done.
不吃了
You've hardly touched it
你吃太少了
I don't have an appetite
我吃不下了
De-wei's here
德伟来了
I didn't know you were coming
我不知道你要来
Otherwise
知道的话
I would've done something about the way I look...
我会先弄一弄
I'm a mess
你看我这个样子
We haven't really talked for ages
我们好久没有好好聊一聊了
Do you remember
记不记得
How we'd talk half the night sometimes
我们以前一聊就到半夜才睡觉
I often wonder
我常常在想
If we know each other so well now
我们是不是真的这样深刻地了解彼此
That there's no need for words
已经不需要语言了
Or is this what marriage does to people?
还是结婚以后都是一样
Leaves them with nothing left to say?
已经没有什么话好说了
I know
我知道
There are plenty of problems
你在外面遇到的
waiting you to solve
都是一些要解决的问题
And worries you want to forget
要忘记的烦恼
I know the last thing you want when you come home
所以你不希望一见到我
Is to go through all that hassle again
就去谈那些你想忘记的事情
But
可是
I try... I've tried so hard
我 我一直在努力
To find something else we could discuss
找一件我们可以共同讨论的问题
It's hard...
好难
Harder than any test I can think of.
比我们以前在学校里任何考试都难
The whole society seems designe to tear husband and wife apart...
这个社会好像故意要把丈夫跟太太分开
Men have their male places to go, and
男人有男人活动的场合
women have a world of their own
女人有女人的范围
Sunday is the only time left to be together.
想在一起的时候好像只有礼拜天
But you said
可是你说
Sunday is your basketball day.
那是你打球的日子
So... what day does that leave for us?
那 那还有哪一天呢
I know people who say our problem's no kids.
有人说 我们的问题是我们没有孩子
I disagree.
可是 我不觉得
If we can't convince even ourselves
因为 如果我都没有办法告诉自己
Life means happiness and contentment
生命是有把握的幸福
How can we ever bring a child into the world?
我怎么可以对另外一个生命说
Come with me, I'll bring you happiness
只要你来我就可以给你幸福
That would be irresponsible.
这是不负责任的
Don't you agree?
你说对不对
These days I've been sleeping heavily
我这几天在昏睡的时候
And while I was sleeping
我一直有个感觉
I couldn't stop seeing these years as a dream
我觉得 这些年来就像一场梦
Our marriage was yesterday... just before I slept
结婚是昨天睡觉前的事
We forget dreams. Don't we?
梦 可以把它忘掉是不是
Can't we?
好不好
Mrs. Cheng...
太太 那个
De-wei must be busy lately
德伟大概一直很忙是吧
Jia-li
佳莉 来
Come
过来啊
Mom.
妈
I am disappointing you?
你现在看我这个样子
Will you blame me?
你会不会责备我
I was wrong.
我 那时候错了
Mom
妈
Have you ever been afraid?
你害怕过
Afraid that papa would walk out someday?
害怕爸爸有一天会抛弃你吗
That there'd be no one to take care of you?
没有人照顾你
He's always been such a child. What is there to be afraid of?
他一直是个小孩子
It was I who took care of him!
都是我在照顾他
I scare of nothing.
我有什么好怕的
It's a change for me to make the move
这次总算不是被人家抛弃的
instead of waiting to be walked out on
是我自己主动要求离开的
Hsiao-jiang's too young
小江还太年轻
There's so much he has yet to do
他还有很多事情要去做 要去闯
I guess I knew all along
其实我早就知道
Nothing much would come out of it
我跟他在一起不会有什么结果的
Thank God we were reasonably in control when we broke up,
好在我们分手的时候
No violence or bloodshed!
两个人都很理智也没有什么暴力行为
De-wei's pretty much the same
德伟还是老样子
Even a little busier than before
或许比以前更忙
He's usually not at home.
比以前更不常在家
But I have this kind of premonition...
可是我有一种 说不出来的凤觉
That he's going through something
他现在好像已经有转变了
Just last week he took me out walking for a change
前几天他还带我去郊游
But on the last couple of days
其实这几天
Who knows where he's gotten himself off to
他又不知道跑哪里去了
I slowly appreciate
不过慢慢地
just how much pressure he's under
我可以感觉到他工作上的压力
I could almost feel it in my bones this last time
在他这次消失以前
He went off.
我几乎都可以感觉的到
I guess I'm getting used to it
我想我是习惯了
The way he comes and goes
他会消失一阵子然后又会回来
But I think
不过我想
If we can look at the bright side,
如果我们都往好的方面去想
And trust each other enough
给彼此充份的信任
I think we'll pull through
结果应该不会太差吧
We've found new hope and beginning
这么多年来我们总算又有了新的开始
After all these years
新的希望
Babe, why don't you sleep?
乖宝贝 怎么不睡
Why are you awake?
怎么起来了呢
What's wrong
怎么搞的啊
Look
你看
What's that?
那是什么
A bird.
是个小鸟
A bird is saying good morning to babe.
小鸟跟宝贝说早安
Mrs. Cheng
程太太
When exactly was it
你最后一次见到你丈夫
That you last saw your husband, Mrs. Cheng?
到底是在什么时候
Can you describe what he was wearing?
他的穿着到底是什么样子
Do you suppose he was in some kind of trouble?
他在外面是不是会有什么麻烦
Just who has he spent the last few days with?
他这几天到底会跟什么样的人在一起
I really have no idea!
我真的不知道
You mean there's not a single thing
难道你连一点点资料
you can give us to work on?
都不能提供我们警方参考吗
Forget it.
算了 算了啦
Let's get on with the search. We can talk later
先去打捞 再来说啦
Let's go. - How can I make my report
走啦一不是 她这么不合作
with her humming and hawing like this?
叫我们怎么查案
All I'm asking is whether or not it's her husband!
到底是不是她丈夫
What kind of a wife can't answer a question as simple as that?
这个做太太的 到底是怎么做的
What are they up to now?
他们现在在干什么
What are you doing here?
你怎么会跑来
It's a little off the beaten track, isn't it?
这地方还真不好找
I wanted to talk a few things over with you.
我来是想告诉你一些事情
But there's no way to call you here
这儿又没有电话
Anyway, I thought I'd better tell you in person.
其实 也应该亲自跑一趟
You know
你知道
I grew up with De-wei
德伟从小跟我一起长大
We've played basketball together all our lives.
一起打球
Which makes it all the more difficult for me to tell.
现在 这我就不太敢说了
Befero I drove here,
在我开车来这里之前
I checked with the company,
我大略向公司查了一下
No one knows what happened to the 5 billion dollars in securities
德伟个人向公司负责的五千万
that De-wei was responsible for!
现在不知道在哪里
I also heard that recently
而且 我也同时听说
He's hussled up quite a pile of cash.
他最近赃了我们一大堆现款
It's my guess that your house, car, and
我猜你们现在的房子 车子 还有不动产
Have all been mortgaged off
都已经被押现了
Of course these are only rumors and speculation
当然 这只是道听途说
It'll all take a day or two to confirm
要查明真相 还需要几天的时间
But I have a certain sixth sense about this kind of thing
不过 我对这种事是比一般人敏感
He already...
可是 他已经
Let me finish. The real news is that
你听我说完 最重要的一点是
He left the country a few days ago
他前几天已经出国了
You mean... that's not De-wei out there?
你是说这不是他
With no evidence so far
这还不一定
We can't jump to conclusions
在还没有查明任何真相之前
Just a minute.
等一下
Who told you all of this?
你是听谁说的
I spoke to a close friend of De-wei's
上午接到你电话以后
After you called this morning
我去问过一个和德伟满熟的朋友
Not that "friend" they call Hsiao Hui, by any chance?
那个叫小惠的
Everything went blank
上午和你通完电话
the moment you hung up
我眼前一阵空白
That's not something that happens to me everyday
我是很少会这样子的一个人
Hello,
喂
I'm looking for your general manager
找你们总经理
I've been to that beach, once or twice with De-wei.
那个海边啊 我跟德伟偶尔去去
In fact, we went there last week
上个礼拜嘛
Just before he went to Japan
我还跟他去过一次
What, he went to Japan?
什么 你说他去了日本
You didn't know?
你不知道啊
I thought it was you who sent him
我还以为是你派他去的
What's he doing in Japan?
他去日本干什么
No wonder I haven't seen him around
怪不得这几天都没看到他
He must be back by now
那他大概是已经回来了
Have they found his body yet?
他们有没有捞到他的尸体
Not yet
没有
But they found a medicine bottle
不过他们在海滩找到一个
Which belongs to De-wei
属于德伟的药瓶
Jia-li said it was a psychiatrist's prescription
佳莉说 是一个心理医生开给他的药
That's what got the police onto her in the first place
警察也就是因为这个才找到佳莉的
That could just as easily be the bottle
也许这个药瓶
De-wei dropped on the beach last week
根本就是德伟上个礼拜掉在海边的
Medicine bottle... too much of a coincidence.
药瓶 太巧合了
If that's really his game...
如果真要是这样
What kind of medicine was it?
那这到底是什么药呢
The doctor prescribed it...
是医生开的
An anxiety suppressant.
一种抗忧郁剂
You know how De-wei.
你是知道德伟的
He's been under a lot of pressure from work
最近他心理压力太大 工作太忙
And the way things are at home
还有家里
Come on. Come with me to the beach
走 我们去现场一趟
We have to let them know about this
这个要让他们知道
You go ahead
你自己去
I'm not going to be dragged back into that mess!
我可不愿再被牵连进去
How can you refuse to become involved
一个好朋友可能发生这么大的事
When a friend is in this kind of trouble?
你说你不愿意被牵连
This whole thing with De-wei.
德伟的事
You've known all along, haven't you?
其实你全都知道 是不是
But you're not letting on...
你只是不愿意讲
Come to think of it
其实你和德伟之间
Who could possibly know
还有好多好多事
All that's gone on between De-wei and you?
没有别人知道
Only you, right?
只有你知道 对不对
There is nothing so big or bleak at work
我们公司里 没有这么多事
send him running off to a psychiatrist, taking all these medicines
多到德伟要去看医生 吃药
What other pies have you two gotten your fingers into?
你和他在外面还搞些什么其它别的
What concern is it of mine if his side interests go bust?
他在外面搞东西搞垮了 那是他的事
I'm just helping him out. Is that a crime?
我只是帮他的忙 不可以吗
Helping him out?
帮忙
De-wei...
德伟
First you use De-wei then you try to capitalize on our contracts
你先利用了德伟 再利用了我们的关系
But now you want out.
现在你屈开了 是不是
You can go it alone, huh?
你罩得住了 是不是
Shouting's not going to change things.
你用不着跟我大吼小叫的
Lin
小林
I always though you were the sharpest, coolest of them all
我一直以为你是最冷静 最精明的
You say De-wei went to Japan.
冈U才你说德伟去了日本
What's he doing in Japan?
他去日本干什么
He's not there on any business of mine.
他不是去替我打工的
That's for sure.
这个我知道
I can find out myself.
这个我自己可以查得出来
I'm going back to the office now
我现在就回公司查
I warn you don't ever cross my path again
只是你以后不要再给我碰到
Listen sonny
小弟弟 你老哥哥在混的时候
You are still a baby
你还在地上爬
Go on, run to Mommy now
去啊 去给你妈味抱抱
It wasn't till I got back to the office
我回到公司
That I learnt about the money.
才知道关于钱的事情
The truth is, I feel very close to De-wei
其实我还是满喜欢德伟的
50 million dollars can buy
几十年的交情
Twenty-odd years of friendship
不是五千万可以买得回来的
Maybe it all went too smoothly in the beginning
也许 我们开始得太顺了
With business so good
前几年钱也好赚
Somehow De-wei got it into his head
给德伟一个错觉
That making money was a piece of cake
认为赚钱就是这么容易
Perhaps it was my fault
这也许是我的错
I've got to go
走了
I came to such different conclusions
我开车来的时候
On my way here.
一直在想 有两种想法
At first, I was sure that's him out there
第一这就是他
Then. I got thinking we'd got it all wrong
第二 这根本就不是那么回事
That bottle they found...
他们捡到的药瓶
Could be the one De-wei tossed away last week
也许是德伟上星期甩在这的
And now,
然后呢
He might be fooling aournd somewhere in Taipei
也许他现在正在台北什么地方晃 好好的
However, base on my instinct
我个人的直觉判断
Chances like that are low
这两种可能性都很小
But going off to Japan like that
他手边有那么多的现款
With all that cash in his pocket,
又去了日本
He'd been planning that some time now
这他已经准备了很久了
Without anybody's knowledge
只是我们都不知道
He might even have gotten himself some South American passport
也许他根本有了南美哪个国家的护照
So you think he's not coming back?
你是认为他不会再回来
Let me put it this way
我应该这么讲
If it were me, I wouldn't come back
如果我是他 我就不会回来了
You know what I mean?
你懂我的意思吗
I could be wrong
也许我错了
There could be any number of possible explanations
当然 其它几种情况也都有可能
Think it over, I have to go
你想一想 我先走了
Think of it this way, whatever the explanation
你这样想 每一种情况的后果
Things end up pretty much the same for you
其实对你来讲没有什么很大的分别
Don't they?
对不对
Time is so overwhelming.
时间的力量是那么地伟大
It's frightening
也是那么地可怕
Papa died, and the clinic's dying too
爸爸去世了 医院也跟着被淘汰
The world's left us all behind
我也跟着医院被世界所遗忘了
Remember the night you ran away?
记得你离家出去那天的晚上
We were talking here, quietly for so long
我们就现在一样静静地谈了很久
Do you remember?
你还记得吗
I heard things aren't going too well with you and De-wei
听说你跟德伟最近处得不太融洽 是吗
If I had known this is what we'd become
假如我知道以后我们会变成这个样子
I would never have come so naively to talk with you that night
那天晚上 我就不会那么天真地跑去找你谈
With one thing and another, look at the state of things now
可是事情已经演变到现在这个局面
And yet, at last I know now how to set things right
我想我已经知道应该怎么去改进
Between De-wei and me
我跟德伟关系的方法
What do you have in mind?
什么方法
I must give him my complete trust
我想 我应该给他完全的信任
Do you really trust De-wei?
你相信德伟吗
The one lesson I've learnt best in life
也许 我这一生当中 所学到最好的教训
Is that everything depends on yourself.
就是这个
I depent on myself all through my life
我这一辈子一切都靠自己
Once, I blindly followed someone else...
可是我却盲目去相信了一个人
You should never do that
不要太盲目地去相信任何一个人
Jia-li, once I believed too much in Papa
佳莉 当初我就是太信任了爸爸
Look at me now
你看我现在
Following him
随着他
Following all this that time has left behind
随着这一切 都被时间所遗忘了
But if you came to me again like you did that night you left
如果你离开家那天晚上的事 是发生在现在
I don't think Id be able to tell you anything different
我还是一样地会跟你讲同样的话
I know it was partly my words that gave you the courage
也许 我所说的那些话 是给了你那种
To leave home.
鼓励你离开家的那种暗示
But my real intention
可是 我最主要的意图
Was that you'd learn to rely on yourself
是希望你完全地信赖自己
And come to make your own decisions
和用自己的方式去做一个选择
It's my guess
我可以猜的到
That you're facing the same kind of choice again now
你现在所面临的 还是同样的问题
We kept this fragile silence for a long time
我们之间保持了一段长时间的沉默
Jia-li's eyes were fixed, looking out the window and beyond
佳莉的眼神凝聚在很遥远的地方
She seemed to be quietly surveying all those distant meJia Senes
似乎是省视那些长久以来的记忆
Or perhaps she just didn't want to look too directly at me
还是她不愿意正视我
For fear I'd see how moved she was
让我直接注意到她的激动
Whatever the reason,
我只觉得
I felt it would be simply cruel to press her now
现在最残忍的
For the rest of what happened that day on the beach
就是追问她那天在海滩上又发生了什么事
Or what the investigations might have turned up
结局到底是怎么样的
There was an emergency company meeting that
佳莉的公司有紧急的会议
Jia-li was called to convene.
等她主持
So she had to hurry off.
她必须立刻回去
It was only when we were saying goodbye
就在告别的时刻里
That I realized
我突然想起来
I still hadn't asked after Jia-sen
我还没问她佳森的情况
After all, that was my main motive in coming
这毕竟是我和她见面前最想知道的
It was only then that I learnt
佳莉告诉我
Jia-sen died of cancer the previous winter
佳森前年得了肝癌 拖到去年冬天
The family clinic was now an apartment block
林外科诊所已经改建成公寓
Jia-li told me how, in his last couple of days
佳莉说 佳森在医院中最后几天
Jia-sen woke suddenly one day from deep sleep
有一次突然从昏迷中清醒过来
It feels like the two-o'clock sun
我想 这一定是下午两点多的阳光吧
Taking the winter away
它让我不觉得这是冬天
Just like the sunlight in the spring
反而像极了阳光普照的春天
When even the birds are singing
我好像听到鸟叫的声音
Things seem to be coming to life all around me
世界似乎又在我身边苏醒过来
I want so much to know it all from the start
我渴望再重新认识我周围的一切
What a violent contrast
这是多么强烈的矛盾啊
Everything here is so cold
周围一切冰冷
But my heart is hot and beating hard
而我的心脏却仍然那么热烈地跳动着
With some strange,
到底是那一种无形的力量
Formless energy against that icy world
让它在这冰冷的世界里
What makes it work so hard I wonder?
还这么卖力地工作着
But, I'm happy enough
不过 我已经够幸福了
Am I wrong?
不是吗
You know? Just keeping this small life going so long
能拥有这么渺小的生命这么久
Is something worth celebrating in itself
已经是值得庆幸的奇蹟了
To this day, I still have no idea
一直到现在我还是不知道
Whether it was De-wei who drowned
海滩上那个死者到底是不是德伟
But that's not important anymore
但是这个似乎已经不重要了 不是吗
What really matters is that
重要的是这个小女孩已经长大
The girl I once knew has grown into the woman
成为一个完美的妇人了
Who walked away from
我相信她的成长
That day on the beach.
也全是从海滩的那一件事情发生以后开始的吧